<!DOCTYPE html>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
    <title></title>
</head>
<body>
    
	<h1><p align=center>Task 6</h1>

   <br >
       1.Add any image to your page and specify image map for it.  </br>
    2.Each image map item should contain title attribute and anchor to
     the text or any other content below the image.<br />
   
    <hr >

    <P><IMG SRC="solarsys.gif" WIDTH=504 HEIGHT=126 BORDER=0
    ALT="Solar System" USEMAP="#SystemMap">

<MAP NAME="SystemMap">
    <AREA SHAPE="rect" COORDS="0,0,82,126"
        title="Sun" HREF="http://uk.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A1%D0%BE%D0%BD%D1%86%D0%B5">
    <AREA SHAPE="circle" COORDS="90,58,3"
        title="Mercury"  href="#Mercury" >
    <AREA SHAPE="circle" COORDS="124,58,8"
        title="Venus"    href ="#Venus">
    <AREA SHAPE="circle" COORDS="162,58,10"
        title="Earth"    href="#Earth">
    <AREA SHAPE="circle" COORDS="203,58,8"
        title="Mars"     href="#Mars">
    <AREA SHAPE="poly" COORDS="221,34,238,37,257,32,278,44,284,60,
        281,75,288,91,267,87,253,89,237,81,229,64,228,54"
        title="Jupiter"  href="#Jupiter">
    <AREA SHAPE="poly" COORDS="288,19,316,39,330,37,348,47,351,66,
        349,74,367,105,337,85,324,85,307,77,303,60,307,50"
        title="Saturn"  href="#Saturn">
    <AREA SHAPE="poly" COORDS="405,39,408,50,411,57,410,71,404,78,
        393,80,383,86,381,75,376,69,376,56,380,48,393,44"
        title="Uranus"  href="#Uranus">
    <AREA SHAPE="poly" COORDS="445,38,434,49,431,53,427,62,430,72,
        435,77,445,92,456,77,463,72,463,62,462,53,455,47"
        title="Neptune"   href="#Neptune">
    <AREA SHAPE="circle" COORDS="479,66,3"
        title="Pluto" href="#Pluto">
</MAP>
        <h2><a name="Mercury"><center><font size=6>Mercury</font></center></a></h2>
        <p>
            &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Mercury is the innermost of the eight planets in the Solar System.
             It is also the smallest, and its orbit has the highest
             eccentricity of the eight.It orbits the Sun once in about 88
             Earth days, completing three rotations about its axis for every
             two orbits. Mercury has the smallest axial tilt of the Solar 
            System planets. The perihelion of Mercury's orbit precesses
             around the Sun at an excess of 43 arcseconds per century beyond
             what is predicted by Newtonian mechanics, a phenomenon that was
             explained in the 20th century by Albert Einstein's General Theory of Relativity.
        </p>
        <h3><a name="Venus"><center><font size=6>Venus</font></center></a></h3>
        <P>
           &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Venus  is the second planet from the Sun, orbiting it every 224.7 Earth days.The planet is named after Venus, the Roman goddess of love and beauty. After the Moon, it is the brightest natural object in the night sky, reaching an apparent magnitude of −4.6, bright enough to cast shadows.Because Venus is an inferior planet from Earth, it never appears to venture far from the Sun: its elongation reaches a maximum of 47.8°. Venus reaches its maximum brightness shortly before sunrise or shortly after sunset, for which reason it has been known in ancient time as the Morning Star or Evening Star. It was not until the Hellenistic era (300-200 BC) astronomers realised it was one object and gave it the name it has today.
Venus is classified as a terrestrial planet and it is sometimes called Earth's "sister planet" owing to their similar size, gravity, and bulk composition (Venus is both the closest planet to Earth and the planet closest in size to Earth). It is covered with an opaque layer of highly reflective clouds of sulfuric acid, preventing its surface from being seen from space in visible light. Venus has the most dense atmosphere of all the terrestrial planets in the Solar System, consisting of mostly carbon dioxide. The atmospheric pressure at the planet's surface is 92 times that of the Earth. Venus has no carbon cycle to lock carbon back into rocks and surface features, nor does it seem to have any organic life to absorb it in biomass. Venus is believed to have previously possessed oceans, but these evaporated as the temperature rose owing to the runaway greenhouse effect.The water has most probably photodissociated, and, because of the lack of a planetary magnetic field, the free hydrogen has been swept into interplanetary space by the solar wind. Venus' surface is a dry desertscape with many slab-like rocks, periodically refreshed by volcanism.

            <h3><a name="Earth"><center><font size=6>Earth</font></center></a></h3>
            <p>
              &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;  Earth  (or the Earth) is the third planet from the Sun, and the densest and fifth-largest of the eight planets in the Solar System. It is also the largest of the Solar System's four terrestrial planets. It is sometimes referred to as the world, the Blue Planet,[20] or by its Latin name, Terra.[note 6]
Earth formed 4.54 billion years ago, and life appeared on its surface within one billion years.[21] The planet is home to millions of species, including humans.[22] Earth's biosphere has significantly altered the atmosphere and other abiotic conditions on the planet, enabling the proliferation of aerobic organisms as well as the formation of the ozone layer which, together with Earth's magnetic field, blocks harmful solar radiation, permitting life on land.[23] The physical properties of the Earth, as well as its geological history and orbit, have allowed life to persist during this period. Estimates on how much longer the planet will to be able to continue to support life range from a mere 500 million years, to as long as 2.3 billion years.[24][25][26]
Earth's outer surface is divided into several rigid segments, or tectonic plates, that migrate across the surface over periods of many millions of years. About 71% of the surface is covered by salt water oceans, with the remainder consisting of continents and islands which together have many lakes and other sources of water that contribute to the hydrosphere. Earth's poles are mostly covered with solid ice (Antarctic ice sheet) or sea ice (Arctic ice cap). The planet's interior remains active, with a thick layer of relatively solid mantle, a liquid outer core that generates a magnetic field, and a solid iron inner core.
            </p>
            <h4><a name="Mars"><center><font size=6>Mars</font></center></a></h4>
            <p>
             &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;   Mars  is the fourth planet from the Sun in the Solar System. Named after the Roman god of war, Mars, it is often described as the "Red Planet" as the iron oxide prevalent on its surface gives it a reddish appearance.[13] Mars is a terrestrial planet with a thin atmosphere, having surface features reminiscent both of the impact craters of the Moon and the volcanoes, valleys, deserts, and polar ice caps of Earth. The rotational period and seasonal cycles of Mars are likewise similar to those of Earth, as is the tilt that produces the seasons. Mars is the site of Olympus Mons, the highest known mountain within the Solar System, and of Valles Marineris, one of the largest canyons. The smooth Borealis basin in the northern hemisphere covers 40% of the planet and may be a giant impact feature.[14][15]
Until the first successful flyby of Mars occurred in 1965, by Mariner 4, many speculated about the presence of liquid water on the planet's surface. This was based on observed periodic variations in light and dark patches, particularly in the polar latitudes, which appeared to be seas and continents; long, dark striations were interpreted by some as irrigation channels for liquid water. These straight line features were later explained as optical illusions, though geological evidence gathered by unmanned missions suggest that Mars once had large-scale water coverage on its surface.[16] In 2005, radar data revealed the presence of large quantities of water ice at the poles,[17] and at mid-latitudes.[18][19] The Mars rover Spirit sampled chemical compounds containing water molecules in March 2007. The Phoenix lander directly sampled water ice in shallow Martian soil on July 31, 2008.[20]
Mars has two moons, Phobos and Deimos, which are small and irregularly shaped. These may be captured asteroids, similar to 5261 Eureka, a Martian trojan asteroid. Mars is currently host to three functional orbiting spacecraft: Mars Odyssey, Mars Express, and the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter, and one on the surface, the Mars Exploration Rover Opportunity. Defunct spacecraft on the surface include MER-A Spirit, and several other inert landers and rovers, both successful and unsuccessful such as the Phoenix lander, which completed its mission in 2008. Observations by NASA's now-defunct Mars Global Surveyor show evidence that parts of the southern polar ice cap have been receding.[21] Observations by the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter have revealed possible flowing water during the warmest months on Mars.[22]
Mars can easily be seen from Earth with the naked eye. Its apparent magnitude reaches −3.0[7], which is only surpassed by Jupiter, Venus, the Moon, and the Sun. Optical ground-based telescopes are typically limited to resolving features about 300 km (186 miles) across when Earth and Mars are closest, because of Earth's atmosphere.
            </p>
            <h5><a name="Jupiter"><center><font size=6>Jupiter</font></center></a></h5>
            <p> 
              &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;  Jupiter  is the fifth planet from the Sun and the largest planet within the Solar System.[13] It is a gas giant with mass one-thousandth that of the Sun but is two and a half times the mass of all the other planets in our Solar System combined. Jupiter is classified as a gas giant along with Saturn, Uranus and Neptune. Together, these four planets are sometimes referred to as the Jovian or outer planets.
The planet was known by astronomers of ancient times,[14] and was associated with the mythology and religious beliefs of many cultures. The Romans named the planet after the Roman god Jupiter.[15] When viewed from Earth, Jupiter can reach an apparent magnitude of −2.94, making it on average the third-brightest object in the night sky after the Moon and Venus. (Mars can briefly match Jupiter's brightness at certain points in its orbit.)
Jupiter is primarily composed of hydrogen with a quarter of its mass being helium; it may also have a rocky core of heavier elements[16]. Because of its rapid rotation, Jupiter's shape is that of an oblate spheroid (it possesses a slight but noticeable bulge around the equator). The outer atmosphere is visibly segregated into several bands at different latitudes, resulting in turbulence and storms along their interacting boundaries. A prominent result is the Great Red Spot, a giant storm that is known to have existed since at least the 17th century when it was first seen by telescope. Surrounding the planet is a faint planetary ring system and a powerful magnetosphere. There are also at least 66 moons, including the four large moons called the Galilean moons that were first discovered by Galileo Galilei in 1610. Ganymede, the largest of these moons, has a diameter greater than that of the planet Mercury.
Jupiter has been explored on several occasions by robotic spacecraft, most notably during the early Pioneer and Voyager flyby missions and later by the Galileo orbiter. The most recent probe to visit Jupiter was the Pluto-bound New Horizons spacecraft in late February 2007. The probe used the gravity from Jupiter to increase its speed. Future targets for exploration in the Jovian system include the possible ice-covered liquid ocean on the moon Europa.
            </p>
            <h6><a name="Saturn"><center><font size=6>Saturn</font></center></a></h6>
            <p>
              &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;  Saturn is the sixth planet from the Sun and the second largest planet in the Solar System, after Jupiter. Named after the Roman god Saturn, its astronomical symbol (♄) represents the god's sickle. Saturn is a gas giant with an average radius about nine times that of Earth.[12][13] While only one-eighth the average density of Earth, with its larger volume Saturn is just over 95 times as massive as Earth.[14][15][16]
Saturn's interior is probably composed of a core of iron, nickel and rock (silicon and oxygen compounds), surrounded by a deep layer of metallic hydrogen, an intermediate layer of liquid hydrogen and liquid helium and an outer gaseous layer.[17] Electrical current within the metallic hydrogen layer is thought to give rise to Saturn's planetary magnetic field, which is slightly weaker than Earth's and around one-twentieth the strength of Jupiter's.[18] The outer atmosphere is generally bland and lacking in contrast, although long-lived features can appear.
Wind speeds on Saturn can reach 1,800 km/h (1,100 mph), faster than on Jupiter, but not as fast as those on Neptune.[19]
Saturn has a ring system that consists of nine continuous main rings and three discontinuous arcs, composed mostly of ice particles with a smaller amount of rocky debris and dust. Sixty-two[20] known moons orbit the planet; fifty-three are officially named. This does not include the hundreds of "moonlets" within the rings. Titan, Saturn's largest and the Solar System's second largest moon, is larger than the planet Mercury and is the only moon in the Solar System to retain a substantial atmosphere.[21]

            </p>
            <h7><b><a name="Uranus"><center><font size=6>Uranus</font></center></a></b></h7>
            <p>
 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Uranus is the seventh planet from the Sun. It has the third-largest planetary radius and fourth-largest planetary mass in the Solar System. It is named after the ancient Greek deity of the sky Uranus (Ancient Greek: Οὐρανός), the father of Cronus (Saturn) and grandfather of Zeus (Jupiter). Though it is visible to the naked eye like the five classical planets, it was never recognized as a planet by ancient observers because of its dimness and slow orbit.[16] Sir William Herschel announced its discovery on March 13, 1781, expanding the known boundaries of the Solar System for the first time in modern history. Uranus was also the first planet discovered with a telescope.
Uranus is similar in composition to Neptune, and both are of different chemical composition than the larger gas giants, Jupiter and Saturn. Astronomers sometimes place them in a separate category called "ice giants". Uranus's atmosphere, while similar to Jupiter and Saturn's in its primary composition of hydrogen and helium, contains more "ices" such as water, ammonia and methane, along with traces of hydrocarbons.[12] It is the coldest planetary atmosphere in the Solar System, with a minimum temperature of 49 K (−224 °C). It has a complex, layered cloud structure, with water thought to make up the lowest clouds, and methane thought to make up the uppermost layer of clouds.[12] In contrast, the interior of Uranus is mainly composed of ices and rock.[11]
Like the other giant planets, Uranus has a ring system, a magnetosphere, and numerous moons. The Uranian system has a unique configuration among the planets because its axis of rotation is tilted sideways, nearly into the plane of its revolution about the Sun. Its north and south poles therefore lie where most other planets have their equators.[17] In 1986, images from Voyager 2 showed Uranus as a virtually featureless planet in visible light without the cloud bands or storms associated with the other giants.[17] Terrestrial observers have seen signs of seasonal change and increased weather activity in recent years as Uranus approached its equinox. The wind speeds on Uranus can reach 250 meters per second (900 km/h, 560 mph).[18]
            </p>
            <h8><b><a name="Neptune"><center><font size=6>Neptune</font></center></a></b></h8>
            <p>
             &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;   Neptune is the eighth and farthest planet from the Sun in the Solar System. It is the fourth-largest planet by diameter and the third largest by mass. Neptune is 17 times the mass of Earth and is somewhat more massive than its near-twin Uranus, which is 15 times the mass of Earth but not as dense.[12] On average, Neptune orbits the Sun at a distance of 30.1 AU, approximately 30 times the Earth–Sun distance. Named for the Roman god of the sea, its astronomical symbol is ♆, a stylized version of the god Neptune's trident.
Neptune was the first planet found by mathematical prediction rather than by empirical observation. Unexpected changes in the orbit of Uranus led Alexis Bouvard to deduce that its orbit was subject to gravitational perturbation by an unknown planet. Neptune was subsequently observed on September 23, 1846[1] by Johann Galle within a degree of the position predicted by Urbain Le Verrier, and its largest moon, Triton, was discovered shortly thereafter, though none of the planet's remaining 12 moons were located telescopically until the 20th century. Neptune has been visited by only one spacecraft, Voyager 2, which flew by the planet on August 25, 1989.
Neptune is similar in composition to Uranus, and both have compositions which differ from those of the larger gas giants, Jupiter and Saturn. Neptune's atmosphere, while similar to Jupiter's and Saturn's in that it is composed primarily of hydrogen and helium, along with traces of hydrocarbons and possibly nitrogen, contains a higher proportion of "ices" such as water, ammonia and methane. Astronomers sometimes categorize Uranus and Neptune as "ice giants" in order to emphasize these distinctions.[13] The interior of Neptune, like that of Uranus, is primarily composed of ices and rock.[14] Traces of methane in the outermost regions in part account for the planet's blue appearance.[15]
In contrast to the relatively featureless atmosphere of Uranus, Neptune's atmosphere is notable for its active and visible weather patterns. For example, at the time of the 1989 Voyager 2 flyby, the planet's southern hemisphere possessed a Great Dark Spot comparable to the Great Red Spot on Jupiter. These weather patterns are driven by the strongest sustained winds of any planet in the Solar System, with recorded wind speeds as high as 2,100 kilometres per hour (1,300 mph).[16] Because of its great distance from the Sun, Neptune's outer atmosphere is one of the coldest places in the Solar System, with temperatures at its cloud tops approaching −218 °C (55 K). Temperatures at the planet's centre are approximately 5,400 K (5,000 °C).[17][18] Neptune has a faint and fragmented ring system (labeled 'arcs'), which may have been detected during the 1960s but was only indisputably confirmed in 1989 by Voyager 2.[
            </p>
            <h2><a name="Pluto"><center><font size=6>Pluto</font></center></a></h2>
            <p>
 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Pluto, formal designation 134340 Pluto, is the second-most-massive known dwarf planet in the Solar System (after Eris) and the tenth-most-massive body observed directly orbiting the Sun. Originally classified as the ninth planet from the Sun, Pluto was recategorized as a dwarf planet and plutoid owing to the discovery that it is only one of several large bodies within the Kuiper belt.[i]
Like other members of the Kuiper belt, Pluto is composed primarily of rock and ice and is relatively small: approximately one-sixth the mass of the Earth's Moon and one-third its volume. It has an eccentric and highly inclined orbit that takes it from 30 to 49 AU (4.4–7.4 billion km) from the Sun. This causes Pluto to periodically come closer to the Sun than Neptune. As of 2011, it is 32.1 AU from the Sun.[13]
From its discovery in 1930 until 2006, Pluto was classified as a planet. In the late 1970s, following the discovery of minor planet 2060 Chiron in the outer Solar System and the recognition of Pluto's relatively low mass, its status as a major planet began to be questioned.[14] In the late 20th and early 21st centuries, many objects similar to Pluto were discovered in the outer Solar System, notably the scattered disc object Eris in 2005, which is 27% more massive than Pluto.[15] On August 24, 2006, the International Astronomical Union (IAU) defined what it means to be a "planet" within the Solar System. This definition excluded Pluto as a planet and added it as a member of the new category "dwarf planet" along with Eris and Ceres.[16] After the reclassification, Pluto was added to the list of minor planets and given the number 134340.[17][18] A number of scientists hold that Pluto should continue to be classified as a planet, and that other dwarf planets should be added to the roster of planets along with Pluto.[19][20]
Pluto has five known moons, the largest being Charon discovered in 1978, along with Nix and Hydra, discovered in 2005,[21] and the provisionally named S/2011 P 1, discovered in 2011.[22] Another discovery was announced on 11 July 2012, provisionally designated S/2012 (134340) 1, bringing the total number of identified satellites orbiting Pluto to five.[4] Pluto and Charon are sometimes described as a binary system because the barycenter of their orbits does not lie within either body.[23] However, the IAU has yet to formalise a definition for binary dwarf planets, and as such Charon is officially classified as a moon of Pluto.
            </p>
</body>
</html>